<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A quest of enquirie, by women to know, whether the tripe-wife were trimmed by Doll yea or no Gathered by Oliuer Oat-meale.</title>
            <author>Oat-meale, Oliver.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1595</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 44 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 16 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A08436</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 18758</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S110170</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99845773</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99845773</idno>
            <idno type="VID">176513</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A08436)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 176513)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 339:24)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A quest of enquirie, by women to know, whether the tripe-wife were trimmed by Doll yea or no Gathered by Oliuer Oat-meale.</title>
                  <author>Oat-meale, Oliver.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 22 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By T.G. and are to be sold in Paules Church-yard,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1595.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Partly in verse.</note>
                  <note>The printer is purposely unidentifiable.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>England --  Social life and customs --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:176513:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:176513:1"/>
            <p>
               <hi>A Queſt of Enquirie, by women to know, Whether the Tripe-wife were trimmed by Doll yea or no.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Gathered by Oliver Oat-meale.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Imprinted at London by T. G. and are to be ſold in Paules Church-yard. 1595.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_author">
            <pb facs="tcp:176513:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:176513:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>OLiuer, if your name be Oliuer, by your leaue a caſt, for I muſt ſhow in betweene the doore and the wal, that is ſhuffle a letter in betweene your title and Pamphlets which Letter was directed to be let at the two fooles at London bridge: and for my hart I cannot finde the ſigne. Now ſince your Pam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phlet lackes both a Paſſe and a Patrone, I thinke this letter wil fit ye for either, and by wandring among ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie, happen at length into the right owners hands. It followes at auenture.
<q>
                  <p>To Simon Huff-ſnuff the terrible Book-tearer, &amp; furious d-facer of the Tripe-wiues effigies, peace offered with cap and knee, to preſerue all papers from like extremitie.</p>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>HAught minded, and hot ſpirited Simon, I ſalute ye. Underſtanding your valarous aſſaults againſt <hi>The Tricking of the Tripe-wife,</hi> in ſundrie places: I could but commend your forwardnes: and praiſe your aduſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed opinion vpon the firſt ſight, both of the Author that made it, and of them that neuer heard of it before your ſelfe: twas well done, you ſhall finde <hi>Caſtalian</hi> of my minde, that of ſuch ſwift cenſurers hath this ſentence:
<q>
                  <l>
                     <hi>A fooles bolt is ſoone ſhot,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Adpenitendum proper at, cito qui indicat.</hi>
                  </l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>Tut, what tell I you of repentance, proceed, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed, your neighbor Nichol and you may anſwere any
<pb facs="tcp:176513:3"/>
thing you do. By your leave ſir a little: and while I talke, haue ſome patience, glare not with your eyes, fome not at the mouth, ſtrike not with your fiſts, ſtamp not with your feete: I will reaſon reaſonably vppon my honeſtie, &amp; yet I care not if I leave argument, and vſe example.</p>
            <p>A quaint fellow growen fortunate: excelling as hee thinkes both in wealth and wiſedome all his other ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ualls, forges to himſelfe an imaginarie concept, that they enuying his good, intend to haue publike ieſts at him and his late won wife. The moſt of them whoſe good fortunes it was to looſe (as it had been great pit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie to part ſo loving a couple) are moſt Scholler-like Gentlemen, and one of them generally beloued of act that in printing haue experience to publiſh any thing, &amp; at this time is poſſeſt of a worſhipfull place, according to the laudable cuſtomes of this honorable Citie. Now which way in your opinion is beſt to preuent the wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting or publiſhing of anie odde toy: ſhall hee reconcile himſelfe to thoſe that were the <hi>quondam</hi> ſuters, &amp; giue good words, becauſe his widdow hath been notoriouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ridiculous: Or ſhall be run vp and downe the town, with friſkes, and heighs, and fillops, and trickes, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>companied with ſome ſuch wiſe-akers as himſelfe, (Be not offended <hi>Simon,</hi> though you be his companion) re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiling his betters, and abuſing his equalls. The ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample needes no application: and for anſwere your neighbor <hi>Nichol</hi> tooke this laſt courſe. For I haue heard him that trickt the Tripe wife ſweare, till her huſband abuſed him, and your ſelfe conſorting with Nick Trickes miſuſed his whole companie, the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters eſpecially, one of them in kindnes and reuerence
<pb facs="tcp:176513:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
that honourable name yee vſde, vouchſafing both to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>companie and counſell you for your owne good: whoſe good will you rewarde with reproches: but they that touch pitch ſhall bee ſettled, and thoſe that pleaſure in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gratefull perſons vnthankfully required. He proteſts before God, that the Maſters of his Companie, are vtterly ignorant of his proceedings, and for ought hee knoweth are at him offended. He appeales to all the worſhipfull Companies in <hi>London,</hi> eſpecially to thoſe of whom your ſelues are free, whether ye haue not done the parts of intemperate idiots, to abuſe men in autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie without cauſe: and proteſts, had he been but a wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter man, as he is a profeſſor of the moſt noble Science of Printing, hee wound not haue ſuffered the abuſe of his ſupertors. He repenteth not anie thing that he hath written, but is onely ſorrie that he is by an honorable perſonage miſtaken: but doubteth not ſhortly to proue how you haue abuſed one verie nere him. He ſweares that where he hath been a mortall enime to all Ballad ſingers, he will neuer inuaigh againſt them more, if they will ſing at pour windowes a new Tigge, termed <hi>Anie Tripes.</hi> Conſider neighbor <hi>Simon</hi> the contents, to waſt paper be pitifull, and learne patience: keepe a good tung in your head, leaſt it hurt your teeth. Fare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well <hi>Sim,</hi> and commend me to your euerthwart neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Yours to vſe, when ye know how to vſe your ſelfe.
D. D.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:176513:4"/>
            <head>An Eglogue louingly begun and unluckily ended betweene the Tripe-wife, and Trickes her husband.</head>
            <lg>
               <head>Trickes.</head>
               <l>Sit we ſweete Sowce wife on this fraile of figs,</l>
               <l>So ſpite of thoſe that dou our fortunes hate:</l>
               <l>Sleting at vs with Ballads and with ligs,</l>
               <l>Enough to make kinde loue unkinde debate,</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And while we carroll of our diſcontent,</l>
               <l>With ſtrained notes, like ſcritch owles yokeſome cire,</l>
               <l>The roaring riuer vnto our lament</l>
               <l>Shall lend her lowd confuſed harmonie.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>Tripe-wife,</head>
               <l>Ahwere we ſeated in a ſowce-tubs ſhade,</l>
               <l>Ouer our beads of tripes a canopie:</l>
               <l>Remembrance of my paſt ioy-thruing trade,</l>
               <l>Would ſomewhat caſe my preſent miſerie,</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But ſince I trotted from my trotter ſtall,</l>
               <l>And figd about from neates feete neatly dreſt:</l>
               <l>I finde no pleaſure nor content at all,</l>
               <l>But liue diſdaind, diſpiſde, abuſde, diſtreſt.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:176513:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <head>Trickes.</head>
               <l>Why here are ſweetes, ſweete Loue, for ſent and taſt,</l>
               <l>Frute from the Straights, Spaine, Candie, Barbarie,</l>
               <l>Indian Tobacco, humors moyſt to waſt,</l>
               <l>Thou knowſt I have a pipe for thee and mee.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Succades and comfets, barts help Cynamom:</l>
               <l>Pepper cold in the maw, hot on the tung:</l>
               <l>Seny to purge, health keeping Balſamum,</l>
               <l>And Mace, to make thy vizard ſmooth and young.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>Tripe-wife.</head>
               <l>Out vpon all this traſh, your drugs, your ſpice,</l>
               <l>Twere well if I had neuer ſeene your houſe:</l>
               <l>You tear me my viſage vizard, goodman vice:</l>
               <l>But I was yong, faire, neate, when I ſold ſowſe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>Trickes.</head>
               <l>Thy tripes were yong, thy neates fette fat and faire,</l>
               <l>Thy ſowſe was ſweete, and all theſe longd to thee:</l>
               <l>Thy ſelfe wert wythered, old, leane, meager, bare,</l>
               <l>Yet thou and they were both beloude of mee.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But neither thou nor they may make compare</l>
               <l>With me or mine, therefore contend no more:</l>
               <l>The Butchers offalls were thy ſweeteſt ware,</l>
               <l>Mine, of farre Kingdomes are the wealthy ſtore.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:176513:5"/>
               <head>Tripe-wife.</head>
               <l>Accurſt was I to leaue the Butchers fees,</l>
               <l>How baſe ſo ere, they brought in golden gaine,</l>
               <l>The miſtres Tripe-wines name by thee I leeſe:</l>
               <l>That loſſe, their lacke, I ceaſeleſſe doe complaine.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>Trickes.</head>
               <l>Accurſt was I to baunt the pudding houſe,</l>
               <l>Where ſwine facde beautie onely ſate in pride:</l>
               <l>Curſt be the chitterlings, the tripe, the ſowſe,</l>
               <l>And curſt my ſelfe that did not all deride.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>Tripe-wife.</head>
               <l>What dooſt thou curſſe my trade? be this thy paine:</l>
               <l>Run bootles madding, rauing vp and downe:</l>
               <l>All helpleſly gainſt iygging rymes complaine,</l>
               <l>Let cuerie Ballad-ſinger beare thee downe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>Trickes.</head>
               <l>Saiſt thou me ſo, thou Tripe, thou hated ſcorne?</l>
               <l>Goe ſwill thy ſowſe-tubs, loathed pudding-wife:</l>
               <l>My brother Huf ſnuf and my ſelfe haue ſworne,</l>
               <l>Spite of thy eares to lead a pleaſant life.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>With this they part: and ſo the Eglogue ended,</l>
               <l>Tripe was with Trickes, and Trickes with Tripe of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="inquiry">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:176513:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>A Queſt of enquirie of twelue good, honeſt, and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantiall women, vpon examination of certaine perſons, whether the Tripe wife were trimde or no.</head>
            <p>IS it euen ſo neighbour <hi>Nicholſon;</hi> now in good ſadneſſe I am ſory for your miſhap, that a mari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age accompliſhed ſo haſtily, ſhould be repented ſo ſuddenly. Ye man, keepe your owne counſel, and feare not, all will be well enough I warrant ye. You alleadge in your letters, what a blemiſh it is to your credit, and withall, what an inward vexation of minde you are perplext withall, when your friends caſt in your teeth your mariage with the Tripewife, what a beaſtly filthy ſlut ſhe hath beene, and ſtill is, without any hope other amendment. Yet all this is not ſo gree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uous to ye, as the bad reportes that flie abroad of her, that not contenting her ſelfe to be coſoned by a nota<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble drab, ſhe muſt afterward, or at the ſame inſtant, be trimde by that new vpſtart Barbar, who inſteed of Siſſers, was glad to vſe a paire of ſheeres, and for want of a chaire, ſuch as men vſe to ſit in when they are trimde, ſhe muſt aduaunce one foote vpon a Tre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uet, and make the other leg ſtanding fooliſhly by ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarie to the others intollerable follie. O world of iniquitie, where are womens wits: that make no dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference betweene their owne ſecrets, and a Cowe heele or a Tripe, and becauſe their education hath one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly bene to dreſſinge the one, therfore they muſt needs make a triall of trimming the other.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:176513:6"/>
For your ſake good neighbour, pittying your day<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly veration, and according to my promiſe when we met laſt at Ratcliffe: I went to the place you wot of, where (though it was ſomewhat to my coſt, yet nothing is ouer deere in regarde of a friend) I made meanes to get in, euen ſo ſoone as the Queſt of women were newly calde together, and before any of the perſons to be examined were admitted to anſwere. When ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing how orderly they intended to proceede, and that hereby a perfect reſolution might enſue both for my ſelfe and you: I drew foorth my writing Cables, and getting cloſe into a corner noted downe euery thing ſo ſecre as I could, which now written more at large, then in ſo ſmall a roome I could compriſe, I haue ſent ye by my ſeruant <hi>William,</hi> who hath fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther inſtruction beſide to acquaint ye with, whereof I deſire ye to haue an eſpeciall care.</p>
            <p>Firſt, <hi>Margaret,</hi> not your wifes daughter, but a by-blowe (as is imagined) of your predeceſſours, was called before the women.</p>
            <p>Then mother <hi>Meſsingham,</hi> the old true peny for trimming of a Tripe, then <hi>Alice</hi> and <hi>Ione: William</hi> ſhould haue bin there, but was not, marie <hi>Richard</hi> very honeſtly came in, and defended the cauſe very ſubſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tially, ſo did Miſtreſſe <hi>Roſe,</hi> and the partie with the golde Ring on the forefinger. The intergatories for ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amination, were theſe that follow.</p>
            <p n="1">1 <hi>Imprimis,</hi> whether ſuch a woman, named <hi>Doll Phillips,</hi> came to the dwelling houſe of the Tripe wife at ſuch a time, naming the moneth and day.</p>
            <p n="2">2 Secondly, what talke they had beneath toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and whether ſhe brought with her a letter or &amp;c.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:176513:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>
3 Thirdly, who went vp the ſtaires with them, whether any body, or themſelues alone.</p>
            <p n="4">4 Fourthly, how long they taried above together, and whether any ſheeres were cald for or no, or whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they had them ready aboue in the Chamber.</p>
            <p n="5">5 Fiftly, whether they knew them to be vſed or no, for taking away of haire from her head, or the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther vnſeemly place.</p>
            <p n="6">6 Sixthy, whether the Tripe wife had ſo many ſuters as <hi>Doll</hi> ſpeakes of, to the number of nineteene or no.</p>
            <p n="7">7 Seaventhly, whether they knew the man that had beene ſo bolde with the Tripe wife, that threw her on the bed, kill her, and did, or would haue done <hi>ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quid amplius,</hi> becauſe he was the furtheſt in her bookes.</p>
            <p n="8">8 Eightly, whether the Capon and Curkie (by any of their knowledge) was ſent to the King and Queene of Faires or no.</p>
            <p>Other queſtions were demanded afterward, but not with ſuch vrgencie as theſe, becauſe you know theſe were moſt materiall, and (as the caſe ſtood) were moſt neceſſarie to be knowne: yet will I tell ye what the other were, when I come to ſpeake of them as they happened.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Margaret</hi> ſtood laughing, holding her hand before her month all the while the articles were read, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon, one of the women ſharply reprooved her after this manner. What <hi>Margaret,</hi> maide (if ye be) ye ſhewe ſmall ciuilitie, regarde yee not where yee are? you imagine be like, that ye are in the Queenes head in Pater noſter rowe: ye made a wiſe nights worke there, did ye not, when (about you) a man was ſtabd
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:176513:7"/>
ſo farre into the backe, fie for ſhame, be more modeſt, elſe this (and your other trickes) will vtterly marre your mariage, if yee liue to be worthie of ſo honorable a calling.</p>
            <p>The woman had no ſooner vttered theſe ſpeeches, but <hi>Margaret</hi> bluſhing (for ſhe hath a little grace yet left her) ſtood very demurely, making courteſie at euery woord, and promiſed to anſwere euery article truely, according to her knowledge, and thus ſhe began.</p>
            <p>Upon the day you name, ſhe whome you tearme <hi>Doll Philips,</hi> came to my mothers houſe, in the ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bit of a countrey woman, ſaying ſhe was ſent from one maiſter <hi>Grace</hi> in Eſſex, a Gentleman profeſſing the lawe, and a very familiar friend of my mothers, for whoſe ſake ſhe was the better welcome, and much talke paſſed betweene my mother and her, becauſe ſhe ſhewed her ſelfe ſo perfectly acquainted with <hi>Maſter Grace.</hi> A letter ſhe brought indeed, which being read, ſhe told my mother, that ſhee had more weighty mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters to confer with her on, which made my mother take her vp the ſtaires with her, not admitting any but themſelues to go with them. The time of their tari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance there, was not aboue three quarters of an houre at the vttemoſt in all which ſpace I heard no Sheeres calde for neither were any carted vp to them, nor knowe I whether any were aboue in the Chamber or no.</p>
            <p>Now concerning your demaunde for vſage of the Sheeres, truely I am perſuaded it is vtterly vntrue, and onely rumoured abroad to defame my mother. For though ſhe was deſirous to haue the ſpurrialles that were loſt, and which I haue often times ſeene when my father was aliue: yet I haue a better opinion of my mother then ſo, that ſhe would not graunt to enioy than
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:176513:7"/>
by any ſuch a bad meane. Yet age now a dayes in theſe latter dayes, ſhewes themſelues ſo ſimple oftentimes, that one can hardly anſwer for them in matters of more importance, therefore I referre yee in this caſe to olde mother <hi>Meſsingham,</hi> ſhe hath beene moſt inward with my mother, and therefore in ſuch a doubtfull cauſe can beſt reſolue ye.</p>
            <p>That ſhe had nineteene woers, I am not able to ſtand directly vpon the iuſt number, but queſtionleſſe I imagine ſhe had (from the beginning of her widdow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head) rather more then one fewer, for I tell yee, my father left her that which made her lookt after, and not ſo much but olde <hi>Saunders</hi> the Sergeant, became a luſtie ſuter to her: but neuer I thinke was widdowe ſo waſht in ſack, Sugar, and good drinkes, I warrant there are ſome that yet ſit and thinke on their lauiſh ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pences, for my mother was outwardly kinde to all, but inwardly enclined to thinke well of no one, for if ſhe could not deepely diſſemble, there are liers abroad, but I name no body, in regarde ſhe may now make amends for that fault.</p>
            <p>Nowe that there was one more ſpeciall in her fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour then all the reſt, we in the houſe haue diuerſe times imagined ſomewhat, mary could neuer perceiue any outward token to be noted: but the woman who pretended cunning to her, threw forth very vnmanner<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſpeeches of the matter that vnder Oathe (as it were) ſhe diſcloſed the man to her, which if ſhe did, ſhe was not ſo wiſe as I tooke her for: my ſelf am but a young wenche, and yet if I intended to beſtow ſuch a token of my fauor on any one, mine owne mouthe ſhould neuer be the trumpet of my ſhame, but rather as I had offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded fondely, it ſhould be lockt in my boſome the more ſecretly, for let the worlde imagine what they liſt,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:176513:8"/>
when they know nothing, I haue both the winde and water ſide of them.</p>
            <p>As for ſending the Capon and Turkie to the King and Queene of Fayries, thats beſt knowne to <hi>Doll</hi> and my mother, for the matche was cloſely made be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene themſelues, and whether on any ſuch condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion or no, I am not able to ſay: but ſure I am our maide caried them with her, and deliuered them to the woman, ere they came halfe way to the king of Fay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries houſe, for they ſay his dwelling is at Paddington, and the maide was diſcharged of her burthen in high Holborne.</p>
            <p>This is all I can deliuer good women, and (vpon my maidenhead) I haue told ye as much in theſe mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters as I am able to ſay: for I had more minde of other buſineſſes for my ſelfe, then either to regarde my mothers couſenage or wooing.</p>
            <p>Call in mother <hi>Meſsingham</hi> (quoth the Cryer) and ſhe will reſolue yee thorowly in theſe running affaires.</p>
            <p>She being come before the Queſt, whimpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring and making courteſies downe to the ground at euery word: deſired ſhe might be no accuſer of her good olde miſtreſſe, for ſhe knew nothing in theſe mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, and therefore could ſay little, but being comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to proceed in the Articles, ſhe pleaded ignorance to all but one, and the knowledge ſhe had in that one was but by bare reporte neither, therefore (quoth ſhe) builde not vpon the trueth of my words, for I receiued them at the ſecond hand, and few things (ye know) are mended in the cariage. It is (quoth ſhe) concerning her number of ſuters whereof I am to ſpeake, and which of them receiued moſt aſſurance of her kindneſſe:
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:176513:8"/>
then thus (after <hi>Dols</hi> owne words) will I tell ye what I heard.</p>
            <p>When the cooſening Drab had perſwaded my mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſe, that ſhe could helpe her not onely to the golde knowne to be loſt, but a great deale more ſaid to be had in the houſe: ſhee demaunded ſuch a requeſt as hath beene ſpoken of, for by the helpe therof ſhe muſt effect the coniuration, otherwiſe ſhee was not able to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed any further: but by the fatth of an olde woman, I thinke no ſuch conference paſt betweene them, at leaſt I am ſure my miſtreſſe ſweares the contrarie, and I tell yee I will not diſtruſt her wordes for more then ſhe is worth.</p>
            <p>Come miſtreſſe (ſaith <hi>Doll)</hi> I knowe one kiſt yee on Chriſtmaſſe Eue laſt paſt, when your hat fell into the Sowſetub, I know yee gaue a good fellow a Ring, with ſeauen Diamonds in it, and the Ring I likewiſe know ye haue this day receiued againe: ſo, albeit I am able to ſay who the man is you do moſt af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, and can tell therein perhaps more then you imagine: yet muſt you your ſelfe reueale his name to me, how he kiſt yee at the beds ſide, vntide your hoſe-garter, and elected ye for his owne with the beſt teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony of good will.</p>
            <p>She ſaith, that my miſtreſſe reſolude her in all theſe, which if ſhe did, (as I will neuer imagine her ſo ſimple, or that at any time ſhe would make ſo ſlender reckoning of her reputation:) I muſt needes blame her folly and great indiſcretion, which doubles the penaltie of the offence ſo careleſly committed.</p>
            <p>Thus much I will confeſſe good women, that my miſtreſſe had good ſtore of ſuters, among whom were diuers of good credit &amp; eſteeme, whoſe purſes launche
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:176513:9"/>
out liberally, and nothing was reputed too deere or daintie for the widdowe: but that I ſaw ill demeanour offered in any one of them, or any ſuch wanton humor in my miſtreſſe, I neither can or will ſay for all the worlds good.</p>
            <p>Many haue beene falſely chargde with matters, as now perhaps my miſtreſſe is at this time: but I leaue all to him to cenſure, that knowes beſt whether theſe reports are true or no, and ſo take this as the vttermoſt of my knowledge.</p>
            <p>The reſt being examined, and able to ſay little or nothing to the articles, the women went alone by them ſelves a while, and finding every thing ſo apparant, that they were not long to be ſtood vppon: they retur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned that the Tripe wife was neuer trimde, yet to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent the worſt which afterwards might enſue, and as women that would not endaunger their credits, they wrote downe vpon their bill <hi>Ignoramus,</hi> whereuppon, the ſentence was delivered in this manner.</p>
            <p>Firſt, becauſe the Tripe wife had failen into this wonderfull ouerſight, and thereby had run into ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny harde opinions: all her other ſuters (aſhamed of their former fooliſh affection, to fancie ſuch an incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant woman, of ſo durtie a trade, and in ſo ſtinking a place) vtterly giuing her ouer: ſhe ſhould thence be ſent to London bridge, and there be maried to him, that had more then a moneths minde to Tripes and Tril<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>libubs.</p>
            <p>Lord how glad was I, when I heard the game go on your ſide, when I remembred what a tall ſerui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor you had beene all her wooing time for her: your hard fortune at M. <hi>Graces.</hi> where you had ſo ſlender entertainement, how you walkt in your Ierkin and
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:176513:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>
tawney veluet hoſe, to view <hi>M. Hubbards</hi> hoppes, when by that meanes you got a bidding to dinner, yea even the beſt place at the boord, namely, to ſit iuſt before your louing miſtreſſe, where all amorous diſcovrſe was faine to paſſe betweene ye in the Cup, for further libertie ye were not admitted. But aboue all, I com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend your ſhorte and ſweete enſtruction giuen her at the window, punching her by the finger, and bidding her looke to her ſelfe, for ſhe was in danger to be ſwine away, and all your market marde. And in faith the merríe night at Cpping was worth gramercie, when the Gentleman your riuall ſupt in your company, and had a prieſt ready, if neede ſhould ſo require. Beleeue me neighbour, you had great reaſon then to be af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraide: yet more then <hi>Hercules-</hi>like, you valiantly held out, in deſpight of <hi>Philaſtorgogh,</hi> the bottle of Sack, and all <hi>Richards</hi> words, which renownes ye to poſteritie, for an vnconquerable wooer, and verifies on your behalfe that auncient verſe,
<q>
                  <l>He loou'd Tripes as his life,</l>
                  <l>Therefore he hath the Tripewife.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>Oh that I were acquainted with ſome excellent wit, who in liuelieſt colours could decipher downe your heroycall fortunes.</p>
            <lg>
               <l>My ſtile is all to blunt and bad,</l>
               <l>To write of ſuch an actiue lad,</l>
               <l>That brought the wooers all to baye,</l>
               <l>And caried the Tripe wife quite away.</l>
            </lg>
            <p>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:176513:10"/>
Thus haue I ſent ye all the proceedings of the Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, and there with (according to your requeſt) my opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of thy bleſſed night, when you made ſuch paſſage to the purpoſe, as the next morning you had the fruition of all your labores, I meane the Garland of your bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding day, to the diſgrace of al the other <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, and your owne eternall commendation for euer. But firſt I pray ye read this Dutie, which was deuiſed by a dere friend of yours, Maſter <hi>Ieffray Kexon,</hi> in defence of your wife ſo much wrongd, and in applauding of your rare conqueſt, the like being neuer heard of ſince the great Conqueſt.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="song">
            <head>A Iigge for the Ballad-mongers to ſing freſh and faſting, next their hearts euerie morning, in ſted of a new huntſ-up, to giue a good morrow to the Tripe-wife.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>O Neighbour Tripewife, my heart is full of woe:</l>
               <l>That couſning Doll the Iugler, ſhould iumble with you ſo,</l>
               <l>I that am your poore neighbour, bad rather ſpent a crowne:</l>
               <l>Than haue ye thus defamed by boyes about the towne.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Abroad in euerie corner, the Ballads doe report:</l>
               <l>That you were trimd unwomanly, and in moſt ſhamefull ſort:</l>
               <l>By ſtanding on a Triuet.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:176513:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <l>to he are what ſhe could ſay:</l>
               <l>She lopt ye of a louers locke, and carried it away.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Alas were you ſo ſimple, to ſuffer ſuch a thing:</l>
               <l>Your owne maids ſit and mocke ye, and euerie where doth ring,</l>
               <l>The trimming of the Tripe wife, it makes me in a rage:</l>
               <l>And doubt leaſt that the players will ſing item the Stage.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>I am ſorrie for your husband, a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>ke good honeſt man;</l>
               <l>He walkes about, yet mends not, but looketh pale and wan:</l>
               <l>That where before he vaunted, the conqueſt he hath got:</l>
               <l>He ſus now in a mammering, as one that mindes it not.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>A number doo imagine, that he repents his marriage,</l>
               <l>And gladly to the ſhambles, would ſend ye with your carriage;</l>
               <l>For all the carts of houſhold-ſtuffe, that came to London bridge,</l>
               <l>Nere pleaſd him ſo, as this one greefe doth rub him on the ridge.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:176513:11"/>
               <l>If gold bring ſuch a hart-breaks,</l>
               <l>Ile none I thanke ye I:</l>
               <l>Tis ſhame it ſhould be ſpoken,</l>
               <l>and if it be a lie.</l>
               <l>But would he be aduiſde by me,</l>
               <l>if it be true or no:</l>
               <l>I would turne her tober Tripes againe</l>
               <l>and let all matters go.</l>
            </lg>
            <closer>
               <signed>I. K.</signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <p>Now all good Ladds, to whoſe reading this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Jigge ſhall come, I would not haue ye miſtake my meaning in the Song, that ye ſhould goe about the ſtreetes ſinging it, or chaunt it at her doore, ere ſhe be by in a morning, No, God forbid, that would but breed domeſticall diſquietneſſe, and if man and wife ſhould happen to fall out about it, I (not knowing how neere the Tripe tub ſtands) might bring him in more dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of Can ſhot then I am aware of. Therefore I pray ye conceit it after my owne entending, that is, a Sorrowfull Sonnet for euery friend of his to medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate on leaſt their fortunes ſhould prooue ſo monſtrous as his and they run into perill of hanging themſelues, vpon ſo extraordinarie a concluſion.</p>
            <div type="description">
               <head>Heere followeth the rare atchieuement of the widdowe, from her houſe behinde the Shambles, how ſhe was conuayed thence to London Bridge, and made a Bride vpon a very ſhort warning.</head>
               <p>Yea marie Sir, now ye come to the matter I long
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:176513:11"/>
to heare of, by reaſon of the diuers reports bruted a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad thereof, and whether it were ſo heroycally acted, as ſome haue heard it from his owne lippes. Was it poſſible, that ſhe (hauing ſuch honeſt well willers and frends, at home at her houſe at dinner) could chuſe no other time to ſlip away, but euen at ſuch a time, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by to diſcredite her ſelfe? Was her coloured excuſe to buy a bat and an apron, and falls it now out ſo that ſhe bought a huſband? O World full of falſhood, O women moſt deceiptfull, when ye are leaſt ſuſpected. But went ſhe then directly to the Bridge or no? No, ſhe went not then thether, but one of her Siſters, counterfetting a ſudden ſickneſſe, the other (beeing the fatter of the twaine) was made the inſtrument of fetching her to an intended Banquet: where wine walking luſtely about, and manie merrie matters familiarly diſputed on, it was ſet downe for an irreuocable determination, that no remedie, the Tripe-wife muſt dine next daye at her louers houſe. But it is wonderfull to ſpeake on, with what zeale ſhe paced thither, her apron in her hand all the way, which ſhe had not ſo much leaſure as to put on, but looked ſtill behinde her, leaſt ſhe ſhould bee caught vp for waight and faſhion. We, as anie kinde heart in like caſe would doo, doubting her comming, becauſe ſhe had ſo often diſſembled with others, trudges to her houſe: but happie did hee eſteeme that loſt labor, when at his returne backe againe he found her where he wold haue her.</p>
               <p>Now the Siſters lay on load for him, becauſe hee had promiſed them large requitall: and how the tyme was waſted in conference, I know not, but wel I wot, home he would not let her goe that night, for now hee
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:176513:12"/>
had her at ſuch an aduatantage, as he neuer expected the like, if he ſhould now let her ſcape.</p>
               <p>But in good ſadnes they are much to blame, that ſay they whitled her with wine, and ſo (after ſome o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ceremonies theretoo belonging) drew a promiſe of marriage from her. It is verie unlike it ſhould bee ſo, becauſe that night before ſhe went to bed, ſhe prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted ſhe would none of him. Oh, but the old dog beide ſure: and though the man himſelfe were ſomewhat ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merous, yet by good inſtructions he began to chere vp his ſpirites.</p>
               <p>Now you that be louers tell mee whether it were hot ſigne of loue or no, when the Widdowe (ſitching a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſleepe by the fire) hee valiantly (coming behinde her) pulled her ſtoole from her, when downe fell ſhe, and lie by or vpon her, with that learned and wittie aduerbe in his mouth, <hi>Keepe the widdow waking.</hi> Well, I know not whether theſe words are able to enhaunt or no, or what ſtrength or vigor the manly acting of them hath: but either thorough them, or her late ſitting vp that night ſhe tooke ſuch a ſurfet, that needes ſhee muſt to bed. And yet me thinkes that labour might full well haue been ſpared, becauſe ſhe had ſo little while to reſt her ſelfe: and riſing againe ſo early, it might bring manie a qualme ouer a wiſer womans ſtomacke than hers.</p>
               <p>But would you imagine, a woman of her tender yeres, little aboue three ſcore at the vttermoſt not dare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, to aduenture on the water in the broad daye light, could ſo ſuddenly conceive ſuch a hardie peece of cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage, as ſooner-timely in a morning, to paſſe through his cellar, and ſo enter a boate lying readie for her, to
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:176513:12" rendition="simple:additions"/>
ſayle ſo farre as Pepper Alley, and there to S. <hi>Geor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges</hi> Church: where becauſe the Church man was not readie, ſhe muſt needes paſſe a larger circuite. But I can tell ye wherefore that was: marrie to ſtop theyr mouthes, that ſaid ſhe durſt not be married by daylight, therefore ſhe deſpiſed two a clocke in the morning: A figge for them that dare not be married at ten a clock in the forenoone, and afterward home to dinner of her owne prouiſon, brought thether the day before. Here was a cunning bob for the reſt. Call ye him a foole or a ſimple fellow, that had the wit to compaſſe ſuch an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployt: Well maſters, ſit you at the vpper end of the table, kiſſe and ſnowtch the Widdow neuer ſo much: there is one ſits nether moſt, hee hath an eye to his buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, and whatſoeuer you but barely hope for, hee is the man I tell ye, muſt carrie the wench away.</p>
               <p>Oh, but well fare the frend that made ſuch haſt for the licenſe: few wooers are beholding to ſuch a deere <hi>Damon,</hi> And not at that time onely did he ſtand him in ſome ſted, but in the countrie likewiſe he ſtucke cloſely to him. If he reward him not well for his paynes, he is verie much too blame: for both his countenance and credite were no meane helpes to him. Hold him then the beſt ſtring to your bow (Neighbour) in getting the Tripe-Wife.</p>
               <p>Thus haue I been as good as my word vnto you, my verie kinde and honeſt Neighbour, in ſending you this briefe collection of your adventures: nor knowe I how to extoll ſufficientlye your great deſeruings, though iniquitie of time ſomewhat obſcure your valor, reproach fully throwing this bone for you to gnawe on,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:176513:13"/>
that had your labour been beſtowed in better ſort, than for a baſket of Tripes and Chutterlings: ſome one or other would haue ſpoken to our Antiquarie, to haue written foure lines at the leaſt in praiſe of your paſſing proceeding. But ſeeing it is no better,</p>
               <lg>
                  <l>Giue looſers leaue to prate their fill,</l>
                  <l>The Tripes are thine both good and ill.</l>
                  <l>What others ſay, take thou no care,</l>
                  <l>Puddings and Tripes are chapmens ware.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="evidence">
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:176513:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>Certaine reports ſpread abroad of the Tripe-wife and her late married husband, whereby if they be ſlaundred or no, let themſelves be their own Iudges.</head>
            <p>FIrſt for the Tripe-wife, that all the time of her widdowhood, her lips were ſo common in kiſſing e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerie one, and her hands ſo readee in receiving all gifts whatſoeuer, tearming each ſuter huſband, and making ſo little difference in outward kindnes, that either ſhe i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>magined ſhe might haue manie huſbands, or diſſemb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly thought to vſe all alike. A fault, wherein if ſhee were guiltie, as it is credibly reported, doubtles it de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerueth generall reproofe, and no milde cenſure of her verie deereſt frends.</p>
            <p>That likewiſe ſhe was verie wantonly giuen, often deſiring like them long kept faſting, the louing morſell of a man. And to ſhowe her folly the more in this one poynt, I haue heard, that with her own hand ſhe made a priuie ſearch in a Gentlemans round hoſe, whether he ware them with a rowle, after the beſt faſhion: or that they were voyd of all good ſhape and making.</p>
            <p>That one of her Siſters, knowing her by nature to bee thus affected, willed him that hath married her, to ſhew her whether he were a man able for the field or no, and what good weapon hee carried about him: other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, there was ſmall hope of pleaſing her, and leſſe to
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:176513:14"/>
be expected of his ſucceſſe.</p>
            <p>Now whether he followed her good counſell or no, I am not able to ſay: but hence (as it is reported) grew <hi>Dols</hi> vnhappie ayming at her throwing vp on the bed: Which if hee did alone, and no bodie elſe, it was the more valorouſly performed: but if he had any pertakers, it was the greater wrong to come ſo many againſt one bodie; for one to one is alwayes counted faire playe, manly and reaſonable, but to oppreſſe by multitudes, is euer reckoned an apparant ſigne of cowardiſe.</p>
            <p>That ſhee ſhould ſweare the night before ſhee was wedded, that ſhe would neuer marrie with the Grocer he was ſuch a logger-head: but if the former condition of the Obligation ſtood in full force and vertue, then I imagine he had beſt right to her, except ſome hungrie fellow deſired to follow, and ſup vp his leauings.</p>
            <p>And here (by the way) the generall rumour is to be examined: namely, that the night the ſtoole was puld from her ſhe had abuſe offered her two ſeverall wayes: firſt to be vanquiſhed by wine, a ſhrewd depriuer of the ſenſes: then daſtardlike to be throwne backward, and more laid on her, than ſhe was able to beare. If thys be the way to get a wife, well may it be tearmed drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kenly done, but neuer to be reputed heroycall, like his o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther actiue agilities: marrie when no better way is left to ſpeed, wel-fare the wine that won the widdow.</p>
            <p>It is ſaid alſo, that he promiſed my brother <hi>William</hi> the preſent releaſe of foure ſcore pound land by the yere (which he was not to enjoy till the widdowes death) if he would (as he did) labour for his ſucceſſe. And now that he hath ſped, hee not onely in this breakes promiſe with him, but in a matter of two houſes beſide, ſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:176513:14" rendition="simple:additions"/>
behinde the ſhambles, the leaſes whereof were by his deceaſed brother made in his name, and conditioned that he ſhould enter on them after his death: but hyr la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die, my new married brother in law now ſayes no: ſo <hi>William</hi> is like to tarrie yet both for the land and hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, But bee of good cheere Brother, you <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the firſt that hath trauaild for an vnkinde requiter, nor ſhal be the laſt muſt loſe by him.</p>
            <p>Both the Siſters (I heare) likewiſe are together by the eares, becauſe the ones rewarde exceedes the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, and there is ſuch alledging, which of them hath beſt deſerved on his behalfe: that while they ſtand con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending, and counting how much they ſhall haue for their paines, he turnes them off with a fillop of the fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, and flatly ſaith, now he hath what he would haue, let them goe ſeeke what they ſhould haue. Siſters, I would haue <hi>William</hi> and you put your gaines together into a bottomleſſe bag: and if at the yeeres end it en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe not, yet ye ſhall be ſure it will not be leſſe than it it is. Marry, (if ye can) turne your endeuors another time to better aduantage: elſe you will bee thought vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, &amp; he that ſo thriues by your labor more fortunate.</p>
            <p>Fie vpon ingratitude, cries poore <hi>Richard,</hi> hee will ſell all his ge<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>gs for a pore pepper come: yet he ſaies if promiſe had been kept, fiftie pounds in <hi>eſſe</hi> at the leaſt ſhould haue fallen to his ſhare, beſide the full and abſolute power of his Siſters trade put ouer to him onely: where now, he is not onely deceiued of the one, but diſappoynted of the other: and his vnkinde Siſter the Tripe-wife, that I thinke will followe fowre ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling euen in her graue, abbridges him of that paltrie prerogatiue, and flatly executes the office ſtill her ſelfe.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:176513:15"/>
What a lamentable Dittie is here in foure parts, of <hi>Nihil habemus,</hi> which doth not ſo much diſturb the ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, as it urgeth diſpleaſure in the hearers. Good people, beware of wooers promiſes, they are like the muſique of a Taber and Pipe: the Pipe ſings golde, gifts, and manie gay things, but perfourmance morali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed in the Taber, ſtill beares the burden of I doubt it, I doubt it: which in my conceipt is a verie pitifull hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring.</p>
            <p>Moreouer I vnderſtand, that verie ſimply himſelfe makes report, how weake his ſtate ſtood before he got the widdow, and that if ſhe had not come when ſhee did, his inkhorn had been drie, and he not able to write one letter more.</p>
            <p>What folly is this in anie man, to diſcloſe his own ſecretes: If it had been ſo, for ſhame I would neuer haue reueald it my ſelfe. But hence I perceiue growes the houſhold diſquietnes, as is ſaid, betweene him and her, becauſe ſhe findes not what ſhe expected, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore wiſheth her ſelfe ouer head and eares in the ſowce tub.</p>
            <p>O what a mournfull mornings worke was that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene my fat Siſter and her, when ſhe taild on Lom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bard-ſtreete, for exchanging ſo much of her golde, and wiſht ſhe were behinde the Shambles againe as well as euer ſhe was: for the roaring of the Thames, (or rather ranſacking of her bagges) ſo diſquiets her night<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly reſt, that her other home was heauen in reſpect of London-bridge.</p>
            <p>Beſide, it is no manly part in him to make <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, how oft hee trickt the Tripe-wife before he had her. Fie, fie, I am content to winke at ſmall faults, but (if
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:176513:15" rendition="simple:additions"/>
ye ſhould be ſuch a one) this were intollerable. Ile bee ſwarne, I made anſwere on your behalfe, where I had a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> check for my labour, I ſaid, I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> layd my life yee would not vtter ſuch a woorde for all the marks <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>, the man is wiſe enough.</p>
            <p>Then I heare how you goe bragging about, brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing forth horrible thundring threates, becauſe cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine bookes and ballads are printed of the Tripe wife: ye ſaid ye had the tricke to out face all the wooers, and ſo yee would ouer dare all the Printers: yee beknaue your betters, calling them at your owne pleaſure, and then turn your tung to your taile when you haue done. What man? it will notſnowe alwaies, neither can you or the beſt tenaunt yee haue, beare downe <hi>Paules Church-yard.</hi> Rather win them with kindnes, for ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremitie avayles not, they know yee for a man and no more, and will take for ye as a man and no more.</p>
            <p>I know a verie good frend of yours, who would bee heartely ſorrie if theſe reports ſhuld be true, &amp; means to talke with ye on them when hee next meetes ye: for my part, I am ſure ye euer found me firme, and ſo vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right vnto ye in wading thorough the cauſe, that as I would excuſe nothing, ſo would I neuer iuſtifie anie thing.</p>
            <p>Ye muſt regard the world as it is, naturally giuen to finde fault where anie cauſe is given, bee it neuer ſo little. And though all the ſtirre about the Tripe-wife be not worth the leaſt piece of a Tripe: yet it ſufficeth that yee haue wonne the ſpurres, from them all, and therefore let me addde theſe, as appendixes vnto your Armes.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:176513:16"/>
A Chirterling rampant in a feld ſowſant, two hag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gas puddings for the ſupporters, a Neates foote clean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly waſhe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> your creaſt, and a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> Tripe to couer all for the mantle.</p>
            <p>So with my hartie <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> to your good bed fellowe and your ſelfe, with all the reſt of my <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> frends. I bid yee heartely farewell, this 2. of Aprill. 1595.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>By him that is more yours than his owne,
Oliuer Oat-meale.</signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FIN</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="conclusion">
            <p>Hold <hi>Oliuer</hi> and thou be a good fellow, and let me in two or three words clap vp a concluſion, before then fully end thy <hi>Finis.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the Sowſe-wiues time of retailing, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> were not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>; but ſince Tripes haue been <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> it ſeemes thou haſt been her ſweete harts Secretarie. Shall I be plaine with thee: I miſlike the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> of thy Jurie, commend thy pl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>mes touching the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports, and giue thee this priuiledge, that neither hee nor ſhe ſhall euer hereafter truſt thee, and therefors if thou haue anie more matter, turne it to me, and I can ſend it to mad Dauie, that meanes to thunder out terrible matter againſt Nicholneates foote, and Huff ſnuffe his neighbor. Farewell till within this fortnight by which time we ſhall either be all <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, or make our <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> endleſſe.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:176513:16"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
